Guide to the Morris and Dorothy Margolin Film Collection, 1947-1982 and undated RL.10157
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Films, 1947-1976; 1
  - Spain, S.S. Queen Elizabeth, 1955, 9; 22.22 minutes
    • Talgo train at San Sebastian station • train ride from San Sebastian to Madrid: mountains, valleys, towns, railroad tracks • tank with "San Sebastian" written on side • Dorothy leaves restaurant near park in Madrid • exteriors of Prado Museum; Dorothy exits with books • Palace Hotel, roundabout • Dorothy walks to sidewalk and toward camera • Charles and Emma Fish; Emma, Spanish-Hungarian-Jewish "gal," Dorothy, and friend goof around, dance, take a bow • exteriors of El Escorial • Dorothy purchases souvenir from street vendor, climbs into car • long shot of El Escorial, surrounding landscape • Spanish girl seated on rocks • view of El Escorial • bullfight; includes a few crowd shots • Dorothy, Emma and friend exit arena • landscape shots, intercut with shots of crowd leaving • Dorothy waits outside of stagecoach • exteriors of Royal Palace of Madrid • Plaza Major; street scenes • villagers stand along side of road, looking at camera • villagers do laundry outdoors • sign: "A Madrid 5km" • man walks toward group with dog • Dorothy poses with villagers on the side of the road • Romani? family walks alongside covered wagon • Avenida de José Antonio • street scenes, including street vendors • architecture, including post office building • entrance to metro • sign: "Puerto del Sol" • street scenes, Dorothy walks toward camera • street scenes of Toledo • exteriors of Toledo Cathedral • uniformed man approaches camera • young boy in traditional garb walks up hill toward camera • more street scenes of Toledo, many including Dorothy • Dorothy has wine with guide in main square of Toledo • Colmar store • street scenes in Madrid • rural Spanish village, barren landscape • sign: "Toledo" • ruins of the Spanish Civil War • bridge over river • views of Toledo from overlook • Dorothy climbs into car; tour guide at car door • more views of Toledo • Morris with Spanish women in front of shops • Dorothy and Morris in front of synagogue in Toledo • sign: "Sinagoga del Transito" • street vendor with donkey • Dorothy on tree-lined path, uniformed men avoid the camera • sign: "House of El Greco" • narrow street scenes, including donkeys • Dorothy and tour guide walk toward camera • Queen Elizabeth ship • Dorothy lounges inside • Dorothy on deck, adjusts headscarf • ocean behind boat • Morris lounges on the deck, waves, walk towards camera • Dorothy waves from deck; sign: "1st Class Passengers Only" in front of her • Morris points at smokestack on deck • Dorothy lounges on deck • people working on deck of ocean liner • high angle shot of Dorothy reading on deck • Dorothy and friends? lounging and drinking tea • friends on board • New York City, Statue of Liberty and harbor from the boat • Dorothy on deck • Queen Elizabeth at dock, unloading cargo • New York dock, cars
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 22.22 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0009)
  - Quebec, Canada, December 1955, 10; 12.03 minutes
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 12.03 minutes (Box 4, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0010)
  - Puerto Rico, Villa Rica, 1958, 11; 16.35 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0011 Puerto Rico, Villa Rica 1958 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 16.35 minutes
    • sign: "4 Dormitorios Amueblados y Decorados por Patio Shop," in ground outside of building • bungalows • three men stand in street, looking at partially built bungalows • cow in neighborhood, the men go over and pet it • sign: "3 Dormitorios Amueblados y Decorados por Patio Shop" • man stands in front of partially built structures, points camera at Morris's camera • pans over landscape of partially built structures • sign: "Nuevos Modelos de Casas Villa Rica Véalos Ahora! desde $8,990" • exterior of Villa Rica sales office • landscapes, including neighborhoods, streets • close-up on poster, blurry • monument: "A la memoria de Ramon Emeterio Betances" • billboard: HNAS Davila Supermarket • billboard: Casa Modelo Villa Rica • billboard: Oficina de Ventas • houses captured from moving car • views of the construction area • neon sign: Caribe Hilton • tourists at hotel pool and beach, including ocean scenes • flamingos • Morris stands like a flamingo among the birds • landscape and ocean from plane window • plane lands • people prepare to disembark, underexposed and dark • travelers disembark from airplane at St. Thomas-Virgin Islands • locals unload luggage from plane • Caribair plane • sign: "Welcome to St. Thomas Virgin Islands, U.S.A. Be sure to visit St. John and St. Croix" • Caribair plane and stairs on tarmac • Dorothy and daughters? pose under "Welcome" sign • sign: too dark to read • travelers sit in terminal • group of (mostly) women look out at scenic view • interior shots of a shop? underexposed and dark • landscapes • locals at harbor, fellow travelers mingle • produce market at the harbor • Dorothy walks toward camera • donkey carries cargo down street • large house • golf course, close-up on someone setting up a shot • group of men play golf • golfers buy or receive? fruit from young man • golfers peel and eat fruit • Morris walks from golf cart, rolls up pant legs, and prepares to swing; golfs • city square, street scenes • unidentified church? • San Juan National Historic Site Visitor Center • sign: "Visitor Center San Juan National Historic Site / U.S. Department of the Interior National Park Service" • parking lot near Visitor Center • fellow travelers waiting in parking lot • interior of Visitor Center? • women at golf course • man stands next to car • sign: "Caribair" • group of travelers waiting at airport, underexposed and dark • sign: Pan American World Airways, underexposed and dark • fellow travelers read newspapers, underexposed and dark • poster: "The Virgin Islands by Caribair St. Crois St. John St. Thomas Now Also to St. Maarten, N.W.I." • technicians? near plane on tarmac • group approaches plane, poses outside, and boards • Morris and unknown woman pose in front of plane, wave, and board • interior of plane • license plate: Tropical Playground T-116 Virgin Islands • aerial view of town and ocean • group at restaurant, underexposed and dark • woman in bathing suit climbing onto and then off of boat • tourists at hotel pool and beach • series of swimmers jump from diving board • unidentified church • street scenes • group walks away from Farmacia la Esperanza • houses
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 16.35 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0011)
  - USSR (Moscow, Kiev, Yalta, Sochi), 1958, 1964, 1967, 12; 35.56 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0012 USSR (Moscow, Kiev, Yalta, Sochi), 1958, 1964, 1967 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 35.56 minutes
    The original film was labeled 1967, but edge code on the 16mm reversal original indicates that sections of this film pre-date 1967; more details are available on the film's Print Condition Report. It is possible, though, that the Margolins took more than one to the Soviet Union in the 1950s and 1960s.
    • onion-domed buildings shot from across river • street scene, traffic • State Historical Museum, Red Square, the Kremlin • goose-stepping guards marching in front of Lenin's Mausoleum • long line outside of Lenin's Mausoleum on Red Square • Saint Basil's Cathedral • children wearing uniforms, holding red flags on Red Square • long line for Lenin's Mausoleum wraps around Red Square • school children walking in line • Tsar Bell • group of school children in uniform • Red Square • building with large columns • street scene, traffic • Moscow State University • view of Moscow from Sparrow Hill, Moskva River • sign: "Hotel Berlin" (also in Russian) • Hotel Berlin and environs • street scenes, including Dorothy • banner in Russian • street scenes, including Dorothy • park, food vendors • city square • entrance arch to the All-Russia Exhibition Center • Dorothy and fellow travelers • the All-Russia Exhibition Center, including sign in Russian • close-up on statue on top of entrance arch • scenes from the All-Russia Exhibition Center, including fountains, statues, architecture, red flags • photographer takes picture of fellow travelers • food vendors • wide promenade with entrance arch in the distance • ornate fountain • food vendors and hungry school children • more scenes from All-Russie Exhibition • sign: arrow points left, in Russian • Dorothy and friend? toward camera • close-up of building, the Bolshoi Theatre? • river scenes, including large ship, Neva River in St. Petersburg? • Bronze Horseman statue of Peter the Great, St. Petersburg • exterior of St. Isaac's Cathedral • street scenes, including historic architecture • construction workers spreading asphalt • exterior shots of the Hermitage • exterior of the Church of Our Savior on Spilled Blood, some scaffolding • architecture, street scenes • Neva River • Battleship Aurora, open to tourists • sailor walking away on sidewalk along the bank of the Neva River • Dorothy Margolin with guard outside of Peterhof Palace • Peterhof Palace gardens • school group touring Peterhof Palace gardens, close-up on faces of young boys • Dorothy poses with a group of schoolgirls • statue • kids play in fountain, sprinkler drenches garden • Neva River? • workers cultivate grass • Catherine Palace • older women sitting on bench outside of palace • restoration work performed on Catherine Palace • horse passes under archway • apartment building? • street scenes • St. Petersburg Mosque, ornate exterior alcove • gates to unidentified, passersby • Smolny Cathedral? • parking lot • unidentified yellow building behind trees • wide boulevard, possibly Nevsky Prospekt? • tracking shot along bridge over canal, Church of Our Savior on Spilled Blood in background • exterior of Kazan Cathedral • exteriors of Grand Choral Synagogue • woman pastes up street advertisements, street scene • statue of Lenin on pillar, flowers below, in Kiev, Ukraine • street scenes, architecture • four uniformed men walk by on sidewalk, high angle shot from upstairs window • woman painting wall • women working on railroad construction • street scene from inside car, framed by windshield • long shot of statue, from across the street • red building with explanatory sign outside • sidewalk scene, open yellow door (sign in Cyrillic) • sign: "Hashian" • sidewalk scenes • exteriors of St. Michael's Golden-Domed Monastery? • intercut with people on nearby sidewalk, inc. Dorothy and friend • open square, large group of people walking toward camera • exteriors Kiev Pechersk Lavra? • school children and others walk by • scaffolding and restoration work • landscape shots overlooking the Dnieper River, fade to black • man walks over to food stand? • sidewalk scenes, Kiev? • street musicians • sign in Cyrillic • blue building, unknown • two uniformed schoolgirls walk toward camera • long shot of Mother Motherland statue? from other side of hill • high angle shot of billboards • memorial statue and plaque: Cyrillic • workers digging in park • scenes of Park of Glory (Park Slavi), including Fallen Heroes Alley, fade to black • eternal flame at base of Obelisk of Glory, surrounded by flowers • view from base of Obelisk of Glory • street scenes as shot from the car, windshield and dashboard visible • exteriors of utilitarian apartment buildings, new constructions • memorial and surrounding greenery • sign: "Intourist [sic]-- Hotel-Restaurant -- Oreanda" • Hotel Oreanda, Yalta • women crossing street, toward camera; includes Dorothy • 1917-1967 anniversary banner for the Red Revolution on Hotel Oreanda • street food vendor • red flag flies among street lights • street scenes, inc. shot of Dorothy and Morris? • beach • Hotel Oreanda; Dorothy waits outside with friend • Dorothy and friend walk toward Livadia Palace • Livadia Palace architecture and grounds • sign in Cyrillic • Livadia Palace gardens and view of the Black Sea, includes shot of women working in the garden • Morris walks into frame and sits on bench • views of hillside neighborhood and Black Sea • Morris with Livadia Palace and Black Sea in the background • landscape • fade to black • white statues, museum interiors • white lion statue at Vorontsov Palace; Dorothy walks into shot • people working on gardens at Vorontsov Palace • Dorothy and friend? walk toward camera holding hands (multiple takes) • small group pauses at top of steps, gardener walks up • landscape shot of gardens and Black Sea, people sit on benches in foreground • Vorontsov Palace walls • sign related to 1917-1967 anniversary • food vendor • people gathering for group shot in courtyard • unidentified building • street and sidewalk scenes • indoor/outdoor food and flower market; seems rural • busts in park; fade to black • children eating ice cream cones on bench, Soviet era posters in background • ice cream vendor, children buy ice cream • garden square with memorial tree and flowers; sign in Cyrillic • hotel; very mod • landscape view of rolling hilltops • unknown rustic restaurant, park?; fade to black • unknown building; sign in Cyrillic • truck transporting logs drives by • Soviet advertisement, perhaps propaganda; in Cyrillic • statue in front of streetlight on road median • mod building, maybe a bus stop or convenience store? • farmland along river • dance performance in a theater • aerial view of city • Dorothy stands by a fence with a view of town in the background • Morris stands in same place with pipe in hand, waves goodbye
    - Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color, 35.56 minutes (Box 3, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0012)
  - Italy, 1959, 13; 31.22 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0013 Italy, 1959 Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color 31.22 minutes
    Includes narration and music. Structured as a story about the travels of a Simca, their rental car.
    • Dorothy walks past young man getting water from pump, poses • Dorothy sits at sidewalk table at café • sidewalk and street scenes • close-up of church facade • Dorothy walks out of restaurant? • sidewalk and street scenes, including produce stand • Dorothy gets directions from man with a newspaper • Dorothy at produce stand • unidentified cathedral • Dorothy at newsstand near cathedral • houses on hillside, street scene • harbor, including docked boats • shops and street scene • Dorothy climbs into Simca car, waving • close-up on license plate of car • sign: Villa d'Este • car on shaded street • another Villa d'Este sign • landscape shot pans to car on shaded street • boat in harbor • Lake Como and environs • Dorothy walks through garden at Villa d'Este • small group of women walk toward parked car, the Simca? • cars drive down narrow street toward camera • Milan Cathedral, with plenty of pigeons outside • Dorothy and fellow travelers • building and parking lot • Dorothy and friends walk toward Museo Teatrale • sign: Museo Teatrale • advertisement for La Boheme at Teatro alla Scala • Milan City Centre: shops, Dorothy and friends, street scenes, fountain • exterior of arena in Verona • street scene • advertisement for Arena Verona • banner: "Arena di Verona - La Forza del Destino - Il Trovatore - Faust"; pans down to street scene • buildings, including Rolex sign • shops, narrow street • clock tower, street scene • statue fountain • Dorothy outside of a cathedral? underexposed • Verona city gate • street scenes, including street performer • statues on building • Dorothy sitting on bench in park, near fountain • exterior of cathedral • directional sign: Roma, Arezzo, Firenze, Il Campo, Duomo • woman walks by eating ice cream • narrow curved street, car drives toward camera • sign: "Costa Larga"; pans down to street scene • Dorothy walks toward "Ristorante," pans up to apartment buildings • Dorothy walks away from Ristorante, toward camera • city square • two women stand by fence near body of water • sign: "San Marino" • signs for restaurants, hotels • shots of Dorothy at Guaita fortress • aerial shot of countryside from Guaita • Dorothy with fortress in background, looking at guidebook • Dorothy at outdoor café table • two women walking up cobblestone street • Dorothy with countryside in background, Vespa? in foreground • Dorothy walks down narrow cobblestone side street • Dorothy near signs • streets crowded with shoppers, including Dorothy • statue and tower • Italian countryside • crowded street, two uniformed men walk toward camera • guards • flag • sign: visas • traffic cop directs (very little) traffic • guards near wall: S. Marino Italia • sunbathers on rocks at water • beach hotel and many umbrellas • beachgoers on rocks at water • water crashing against rocks, people swimming • bikini-clad sunbather reading • beach scenes • Dorothy puts on swimming cap and gets in the water • rocks, waves and beachgoers • marina with fortress in background, colorful apartment buildings, café chairs, boats • men walk by with luggage cart, boats in background • two women with a baby at café • marina, boats • colorful apartment buildings, pans down to boats • crowded street scene with sidewalk vendors, buildings • aerial view with water, buildings, mountains • ocean at sunset, boats and pier? • aerial view of water, town, mountains • colorful beachside hotel • sunbathers under umbrellas near hotel • city square, people gathered around outdoor theatre? • more shots of city square, including monks? and nurses? • monks? or friars? talking, sign in background: Otello • three women stand outside of souvenir? shop • men sit at sidewalk tables • close-ups of buildings on square • unidentified church • crowded (narrow) street scenes, near the city square • close-ups of couple on small balcony, architecture • adolescents hanging out, architecture • city square, Dorothy? crosses square and climbs steps to unidentified church • shots of church, Dorothy? enters • make-shift newspaper stand outside of church, headline about Eisenhower • Dorothy poses near well • Florence skyline from across Arno River; Dorothy enters frame, poses • view down the Arno River, including Ponte Santa Trinita and Ponte Vecchio • close-up of jewelry in window, pulls back to show Dorothy looking in at them • more close-ups of a jewelry window display • long shot of stylish woman in profile, baby toddles around and falls in background • shots, including close-ups, of stylish woman posing, model? • street scenes, some include Dorothy • Dorothy window-shops • Dorothy walks over to fenced bust of Benvenuto Cellini • sign: "A Benvenuto Cellini Maestro / gli orafi di Firenze" • Dorothy by bust, points, poses on bridge, sits on curb • Dorothy window-shops, camera pans to street, including woman with camera • Dorothy at window display of jewelry, points • Arno River, buildings, bridge • group waits in front of bus • close-ups of exterior of basilica Santa Maria del Fiore, glimpse of the crowd • woman in dress poses, model? • street scenes, including street vendors, street sweeper, horse-drawn carriage • crowd waiting outside building • Dorothy talks to stylish woman near car, model? • city square, including horse-drawn carriage • Dorothy walks out of shop • more exteriors of the basilica of Santa Maria del Fiore, including the dome • crowd, people pointing up • street scene, including traffic cop • exterior of Albergo Excelsior Italia, Dorothy talks to man in white uniform • smaller crowd outside of previously-seen building • directional sign: Pisa, Livorno; roads • countryside, bales of hay • leaning tower of Pisa and environs • street scenes near leaning tower, nuns and monks walk by line of souvenir stalls • more shots of leaning tower of Pisa • from tower, Dorothy walks toward the camera • buildings nearby leaning tower of Pisa, and the tower again • Dorothy waits in line at street cart near base of leaning tower of Pisa • group of monks walking away from camera • street scenes near leaning tower of Pisa, including priest riding bicycle • men in jester suits guard passageway • shots of St. Peter's Square, Vatican City • priest takes photograph for family • close-up on statue • young woman climbs onto motor scooter with young man • exteriors of St. Peter's Basilica, complete with tour buses • obelisk • fountain • columned promenade near St. Peter's Basilica • people exiting St. Peter's Basilica? including a Buddhist? monk and a fancifully uniformed man • close-up: Musei Vaticani • people entering St. Peter's Basilica? man perched near entrance • close-up on sign for Monumenti Musei e Gallerie Pontifici • people walk along Vatican wall, past street vendors • sign: "Only five hours from Rome visit Israel the land of the Bible" • buildings, street scene; nun in foreground before frame pans up • Vatican wall and Musei Vaticani archway with statues above, bus drives by, people come and go • Dorothy holds picture, stands in front of Vatican wall? • shot of Dorothy on sidewalk, under café umbrellas • pans to include sidewalk and café • underexposed shot, hard to see • skyline with palm tree in foreground, domes behind • Dorothy walks down curved outdoor steps • church? Dorothy enters frame, walking down steps • shot of Dorothy sitting on steps with church? behind her • Dorothy approaches and interacts with a group of people, perhaps a Jewish-Italian family? in rural setting • women hoe hay, other farmwork • woman walks toward building carrying container on head • chicken and her chicks • donkey with cart, occupied by small boy • men hang out under brick structure • woman walks down steps • street scene with café tables, woman carrying cargo on head, uniformed man • Dorothy (in two different outfits) outside unidentified building, probably in Rome
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 31.22 minutes (Box 1, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0013)
  - Majorca, Barcelona, 1959, 14; 13.53 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0014 Majorca, Barcelona, 1959 Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color 13.53 minutes
    Includes music, but no narration.
    • unidentified cathedral • harbor • boats • historic buildings • street scenes • museum • bullfight at stadium • donkey cart • people • street vendors • stores • windmills • farm • boy milking cow • tourists on beach • people in traditional clothing, playing instruments and performing traditional dances • Barcelona • street scenes • traffic • cars • stores • shops • church • cathedrals • horse cart • buildings • sign: Barcelona • sign: Ritz • last scene: exterior of Ritz Hotel
    - Reversal original, 16mm, sound, color, 13.53 minutes (Box 2, Film-reel RL10157-F16-0014)
  - S.S. New Amsterdam, France, 1959, 15; 27.11 minutes
    RL10157-F16-0015 S.S. New Amsterdam, France, 1959 Reversal original, 16mm, silent, color 27.11 minutes
    • New York City 5th Street Pier • Holland-American Line pier • aerial view of tugboat • S.S. New Amsterdam ocean liner • people on the S.S. New Amsterdam • ship's crew working • Southampton docks • France • shops • stores • sign: "Vernaison" • market • sign: "Le Coq Hardi" • park • taxi • Paris • military tank in the middle of a city square near the Eiffel Tower • sign: "Exposition Napoleon III Magenta Solferino Le Prince Imperial" • Louvre • obelisk • historic buildings • sign: "Place Vendôme" • street scenes • traffic • stores • shops • cars • monuments • Maxim's • sign: "Avenue des Champs-élysées" • cafés • restaurants • Southern France - the Riviera • Carlton Hotel • street scenes • beach • outdoor vendors • traffic • sailors • shops • stores • esplanade • Martinez • aerial view of city • garden • people at beach • sign: "Carlton" • gay male couple? • Israeli flag • sign: "Red Roc" • seaside resort • sign: "Beau Rivage Palace Hotel" • Switzerland • building flying Swiss flag • mountains in background • houses • fields • aerial view of mountain town • sign: "Café Schutzhaus" • snow, snowy rocks